<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ead xmlns:ead="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 http://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd" audience="external" relatedencoding="MARC21">
  <eadheader audience="external" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" scriptencoding="iso15924" relatedencoding="MARC21" repositoryencoding="iso15511" langencoding="iso639-2b">
    <eadid countrycode="US" mainagencycode="US-RPB" identifier="default call number.xml">US-RPB-default call number</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>Guide to the </titleproper>
        <author>Finding aid prepared by </author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Brown University Library</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>John Hay Library, University Archives and Manuscripts</addressline>
          <addressline>Box A</addressline>
          <addressline>Brown University</addressline>
          <addressline>Providence, RI, 02912</addressline>
          <addressline>Telephone: Manuscripts: 401-863-3723; University Archives: 401-863-2148</addressline>
          <addressline>Email: Manuscripts: hay@brown.edu; University Archives: archives@brown.edu</addressline>
        </address>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>This finding aid was produced using the RIAMCO EAD spreadsheet, </creation>
      <langusage>
        <language langcode="eng" scriptcode="Latn">English</language>
      </langusage>
      <descrules>Finding aid based on Describing Archives: A Content Standard (DACS)</descrules>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <archdesc level="collection" type="inventory">
    <did>
      <unitid countrycode="US" repositorycode="US-RPB" type="collection">Default Call Number</unitid>
      <repository>
        <corpname>John Hay Library<subarea>University Archives and Manuscripts</subarea></corpname>
        <address>
          <addressline>Box A</addressline>
          <addressline>Brown University</addressline>
          <addressline>Providence, RI, 02912</addressline>
          <addressline>Telephone: Manuscripts: 401-863-3723; University Archives: 401-863-2148</addressline>
          <addressline>Email: Manuscripts: hay@brown.edu; University Archives: archives@brown.edu</addressline>
        </address>
      </repository>
    </did>
    <bioghist>
      <head>Biographical/Historical Note</head>
    </bioghist>
    <descgrp type="descriptive">
      <head>Collection information</head>
      <userestrict>
        <p>All researchers seeking to publish materials from the collections of the John Hay Library are requested to complete a Notice of Intent to Publish, prior to reproducing, quoting, or otherwise publishing any portion or extract from this collection. Although Brown University has physical ownership of the collection and the materials contained therein, it does not claim literary rights. It is up to the researcher to determine the owners of the literary rights and to obtain any necessary permissions from them.</p>
      </userestrict>
      <accessrestrict>
        <p>There are no restrictions on access, except that the collection can only be seen by prior appointment. Some materials may be stored off-site and cannot be produced on the same day on which they are requested.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
    </descgrp>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <c id="c2" level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Susan Beth Adler, class of 1958</unittitle>
          <unitdate type="inclusive">2019 February 1</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform source="aat">oral histories (document genres)</genreform>
          </physdesc>
          <langmaterial>
            <language langcode="eng" scriptcode="Latn">English</language>
          </langmaterial>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>In this interview, Susan Beth Adler, Pembroke College class of 1958, recalls her decades of professional and volunteer service to Rhode Island and Brown University.</p>
          <p>Adler begins by describing her family’s long history within the Brown community, her mother being in the Pembroke class of 1925 and her father in the Brown class of 1918. She recalls living in Miller Hall and participating in Sock and Buskin – a coeducational theatre group. She briefly touches upon dating and relationships in college during the 1950s before turning to her life after Pembroke.</p>
          <p>Adler discusses her long career at Classical High School in Providence, both as teacher and administrator, as well as teaching at Roger Williams University. Additionally, she describes in detail serving on the Board of Trustees, a branch of Brown’s bicameral Corporation, and on the Alumni Association. Adler also recalls how she developed her voice as a woman in these organizations. She closes her interview by advising young women graduation from Brown today to network within and outside of the Brown community as much as possible.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <bioghist>
          <p>Susan Beth Adler grew up in Providence, Rhode Island with her two sisters. Her mother, Celia Ernstorf, was Pembroke College class of 1925 and her father, Walter Adler, was Brown University class of 1918. Adler attended Classical High School before receiving her A.B. in English and American Literature and her M.A.T from Brown University in 1958 and 1965 respectively. At Brown, she was heavily involved with Sock &amp; Buskin theater.</p>
          <p>After graduation, Adler devoted her volunteer and professional activities to education. She served as President of Strategies for Education, a national and international educational consulting firm. She was an adjunct professor of Education at both Providence College and Roger Williams University and also served as an educational consultant to the Coalition of Essential Schools. She retired from the Providence Public Schools where she was a teacher for 28 years, then Curriculum Director and Interim Assistant Superintendent for Teaching and Learning. The Carnegie Corporation appointed her to the founding board of the National Board for Professional Teaching Standards, the voluntary advanced teacher certification board. She participated in the Carnegie Teacher Assessment Project at Stanford University as part of that work. She was chief reader for the Rhode Island Writing Assessment and a co-founder and co-director of the Rhode Island Writing Project.</p>
          <p>Adler served on the Corporation of Brown University from 1986-1992. Some of the other many committees and volunteer roles she has had include member and Chair of the Pembroke Associates Council (1987-2004), Women's Launch Pad Mentor (2011-present), Honorary Chair of 125 Years of Women at Brown Steering Committee (2016-2017), consistent service on her reunion Gift Committees every five years, the Advisory Council on Admission (2003-2014), the Advisory Council on Diversity (2010-2017), and secretary and class agent for the Class of 1958. She is currently serving on the Advisory Council on Relations with Tugaloo College (Vice Chair), on the Brown Annual Fund Emeriti Committee (Co-Chair), and on the Brown Annual Fund Executive Committee (member). The Education Department at Brown awarded her the Distinguished Educator Award in 2000. In 2013, Susan received the H. Anthony Ittleson ’60 Award at the annual Alumni Relations awards ceremony, the highest recognition given to a volunteer fundraiser at Brown.</p>
        </bioghist>
        <controlaccess>
          <persname role="interviewee" source="local">Adler, Susan Beth</persname>
          <persname role="interviewer" source="local">Howard, Jean</persname>
          <persname role="interviewer" source="local">Bailey, Bernicestine McLeod</persname>
          <persname role="interviewer" source="local">Murphy, Mary</persname>
          <subject source="local">Academics</subject>
          <subject source="local">Administration</subject>
          <subject source="local">Feminism</subject>
          <subject source="local">Jewish Students</subject>
          <subject source="local">Theatre</subject>
        </controlaccess>
        <dao ns2:actuate="onRequest" ns2:show="embed" ns2:title="Susan Beth Adler, class of 1958" ns2:role="MODS_ID" ns2:href="bdr728097">
          <daodesc>
            <p>Susan Beth Adler, class of 1958</p>
          </daodesc>
        </dao>
        <dao ns2:actuate="onRequest" ns2:show="embed" ns2:title="Susan Beth Adler, class of 1958" ns2:role="BDR_PID" ns2:href="bdr:728097">
          <daodesc>
            <p>Susan Beth Adler, class of 1958</p>
          </daodesc>
        </dao>
      </c>
      <c id="c3" level="item">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Rita Duarte Marinho, class of 1979</unittitle>
          <unitdate type="inclusive">2019 June 5</unitdate>
          <physdesc>
            <genreform source="aat">oral histories (document genres)</genreform>
          </physdesc>
          <langmaterial>
            <language langcode="eng" scriptcode="Latn">English</language>
          </langmaterial>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>In this interview, Rita Duarte Marinho discusses her experiences pursuing a doctoral degree in political science at Brown University from 1975 to 1979.</p>
          <p>Marinho begins by sharing some personal background. She describes growing up in New Bedford, Massachusetts, and being raised primarily by women. She sets herself in the context of the Second World War, recalling how her father joined the war effort six weeks after her birth, landed on the beaches in Normandy, France, and did not return home until she was three years old. Marinho also describes her mother, grandfather, aunts, and uncles, who were Portuguese-Americans, and their dedication to education.</p>
          <p>She goes on to explain that after one year of undergraduate education she married her first husband and hand three sons after which point she attended the University of Massachusetts, Dartmouth, for her undergraduate degree in political science. She explains that after graduating in 1974 she decided to pursue her PhD in political science at Brown.</p>
          <p>In speaking of her time at Brown, Marinho shares memories of deeply rooted misogyny in the Political Science department. As the only woman in her cohort, she describes many of the ways she was challenged by her male colleagues, while also highlighting the male colleagues who were her allies. She addresses Louise Lamphere vs Brown University – a landmark class action lawsuit that in 1975 charged Brown University with sex discrimination – and the reaction to it within her department. She explains that despite the many obstacles in the department, she truly enjoyed her experience within the larger institution.</p>
          <p>With regard to her life after Brown, Marinho details her political activism in New Bedford, Fall River, and Massachusetts more broadly, as well as her career in higher education at the University of Massachusetts, Dartmouth, and several other institutions along the eastern seaboard. She concludes her interview by sharing her thoughts on women and the 2019 political climate and thanking Brown for the life it afforded her.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <bioghist>
          <p>Rita Duarte Marinho was born in New Bedford, Massachusetts in 1942. Raised primarily by women in the shadow of World War II, Marinho was taught the power and value of a good education. Shortly after beginning an undergraduate degree, Marinho married her first husband, Robert Moniz, and had three sons. Marinho and Moniz later divorced. She married her second husband, Kenneth Duarte, and the two remained together until his death in approximately 2017. When her sons were 10, 8, and 6 years old, she returned to her undergraduate studies and earned her bachelor’s degree in political science from the University of Massachusetts, Dartmouth, in 1974. She went on to become only the fourth woman to earn her PhD in political science from Brown University in 1979.</p>
          <p>Marinho led a successful academic career beginning as an Assistant Professor of political science at the University of Massachusetts, Dartmouth, in 1978. She worked her way up to be a full professor, the Director of the Women’s Studies department, and eventually Dean in 1995. Simultaneously, she served as New Bedford City Counsellor from 1978 to 1980, Membership Chair of the Women's Caucus for Political Science from 1978 to 1983, Vice President of the Young Women’s Christian Association national board from 1984 to 1990, and Executive Director of the Fall River Regional Task Force from 1984 to 1995. She has retired to Florida.</p>
        </bioghist>
        <controlaccess>
          <persname role="interviewee" source="local">Marinho, Rita Duarte</persname>
          <persname role="interviewer" source="local">Murphy, Mary</persname>
          <persname role="interviewer" source="local">Knox, Amanda</persname>
          <subject source="local">Academics</subject>
          <subject source="local">Activism</subject>
          <subject source="local">Feminism</subject>
          <subject source="local">Louise Lamphere vs Brown University</subject>
          <subject source="local">Marriage</subject>
          <subject source="local">Politics</subject>
          <subject source="local">Sexism</subject>
          <subject source="local">Women’s Movement</subject>
        </controlaccess>
        <dao ns2:actuate="onRequest" ns2:show="embed" ns2:title="Rita Duarte Marinho, class of 1979" ns2:role="MODS_ID" ns2:href="bdr728104">
          <daodesc>
            <p>Rita Duarte Marinho, class of 1979</p>
          </daodesc>
        </dao>
        <dao ns2:actuate="onRequest" ns2:show="embed" ns2:title="Rita Duarte Marinho, class of 1979" ns2:role="BDR_PID" ns2:href="bdr:728104">
          <daodesc>
            <p>Rita Duarte Marinho, class of 1979</p>
          </daodesc>
        </dao>
      </c>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
